[Music]
yes how are you this is Franky frus
calling again for Patrick Boyd sure let
me just
thank
[Applause]
[Music]
you hello Patrick hey how you doing how
are you it's Frank uh not too bad you
know did you have a little time yeah
yeah yeah y i called a little earlier
they said you were out to lunch yes yes
what did you have for lunch oh oh
chicken season a salad slightly healthy
but uh but then with the croutons you
know so yeah it sounds pretty good it's
all right got a good cafe around here no
b no Burgers and Fries oh they do
Burgers and Fries but you know it's
summer it's summer yeah so yeah far away
I sound far away no no no no fire away
oh fire awayed up now okay got a little
bit of an echo in your voice but I think
we're okay with it okay it sounds like
you're in a large room it is quite a
large room this is I'm in the conference
room oh are you on a speaker phone no no
no not at all okay not at all I mean we
could try back or no this is fine I
think it'll it it'll be fine okay all
right okay why don't we start off I know
you have a number of things coming up
that's very exciting as far as some of
your workshops assuming that those are
still go over there why don't we start
off with that and we'll get that
information out to the folks that are
listening uh right off the bat okay no
problem as you may know there used to be
um a holography school in this
location uh some time ago run by edua or
was called Richmond School Richmond
holographic Studios yes and uh so there
was always classes here and this is
where I first came across holography as
well and yeah basically um about 10
years ago the premises was uh taken over
by a company called spatial Imaging
which is Rob Monday and Jeffrey Rob m
mhm and uh but most of and they're
traditionally a display holography
company but for the last i' say eight
years their work has been more digital
make digital Holograms I see now is that
creating Holograms directly from digital
information or are you using some sort
of an interface with a with a projection
screen or something no no no creating it
digitally prining it dot by dot that's
an incredible amount of uh information
that you're processing there are are you
able to do that using just standard
desktop computers now or proprietary
stuff no no no it's a it's a standard
desktop computer that's just that's
amazing yeah no it's it's they're quite
good and they've got a few Technologies
uh that use different methods but
basically it's yeah printing the
Hologram pixel by pixel and that's
mainly used for security Imaging yes I
imagine they're rather small Holograms
oh no up to 50 by 5050 something like
that quite no kidding yeah yeah what
time how much time does it take to print
a hologram that size because I know a
long time ago in holosphere the the
publication from the Museum of
holography I think there was a company
called aerodine and they were they were
doing digital holography and I think
they were doing a centimeter by
centimeter hologram and I believe it
took 72 hours to print centimeter by
centimeter well I think the biggest one
here takes about 8 hours or something
there's one on the wall here and um I'm
going to take measure on me but it's
about twice the size of an album cover
or something like that okay so they're
quite big and um yeah the the yeah they
take overnight I think those things to
produce yeah and yeah it's all done on
Photo resist anyway unfortunately this
isn't my department my department is
traditional holography MH and uh so
therefore they had these Labs which they
hadn't hadn't been the focus of the
business although they have done display
work but it is it's interesting that
holography has gotten to the point where
we can refer to a specific type of
holography now as traditional holography
yes I
know yes it is quite odd but then again
there are I think a a lot of people
working in holography and I know some of
them actually that work with Hol
holography but don't know traditional
holography they're only digital
holographs you know
oh there's one here actually who doesn't
know about traditional holography yeah
how about that next we're getting old
Patrick yeah I know I know I know we're
part of the old school here doing it by
I I imagine that your workshops are
going to be for traditional holography
as well is that correct okay so go ahead
at the moment entirely traditional
holography um you know a continuous wave
laser most of it but we do cover the
pulse
slightly and yeah very traditional you
know on a very heavy table you know set
time and all that you know all about
that yeah and um yeah so um so basically
the labs were here and uh spatial
Imaging thought they'd like to get the
labs used and thought that it might be
good you know time to uh start the
courses again also there's a renewed
interest in holography yeah and uh there
are some new materials becoming
available as well and uh so as far as
recording materials yeah recording
materials yes what out there that's new
uh well the BB plates oh okay yeah so we
started using those are they your
preference uh yes yeah they seem
available and they seem to work they're
not as fast as XA but when you get them
to work they're just as good they're
beautiful yeah and uh I've seen some
very good work by nyaki bergstein using
them you know full color work which is
absolutely
fantastic now do you do any full color
work there with the continuous wave
start on the course hav started full
color we've been doing pseudo color MH
you know which is what a lot of full
color work is anyway um but yeah we we
mess around with tea but at the moment
we're in a kind of
um young stage you know embrionic stage
we're just we just got the labs up and
running we're offering the basic things
in methods teaching holography at the
moment we just doing beginners courses
and at the moment I'm busy trying to set
up a stereogram camera as well so we can
teach that me as well which will be from
a digital input so I see yeah so um yeah
we've got we got the basics of a camera
here which will um make it that much
easier bit of a shame but there we go
you can't stop progress yeah and where
people will be able to bring files
whether they're computer generated or
film or photographs and scan them in and
go directly from the computer that's
your idea that's great how many how many
images per hologram are you planning to
use oh I don't know 50 to 100 I see
quite adaptable mhm mhm when are your
Workshop programs starting up I'm
assuming perhaps they've started already
yeah yeah we've done three courses so
far how long do they run uh a week okay
at the moment it's 5 days and uh yeah
the at the moment we're scheduling them
for the last week of every month and uh
I haven't really advertised it yet so
everyone that's come along so far has
been through Word of
Mouth now if someone wanted to get
information about the workshops on the
web would they go to your personal
website or Is there another website that
you would recommend they go to there is
another website and it is
www. Holograms do and you follow the
link from it says what's new okay okay U
hopefully we'll get a a direct link
because we've after the third Workshop
we decided it had the school had to have
a name so we've come up with the London
School of phography terrific fills all
the bills and I've got to um redo the
web so uh that comes up on a search and
hopefully it'll come up we'll have to
find out if London school is
available or London school or
philography or something like that mhm
do that now your your early work why
don't you tell the listeners that may
not be familiar with Patrick Boyd from
dare I say maybe 20 years maybe 15 20
years ago oh golly now you're talking uh
well yeah it's 20 years now since I've
been involved in holography I think yeah
and you started out with
um I guess what we would turn here here
in the States you did a lot of U fashion
portraiture I imagine yes yeah um well
um I took uh the ma at the Royal College
of Art in holography and uh came from a
photographic
background and I so I guess my first
Holograms actually photographic ones so
the animated ones and um just animated
images and for some reason then I was
into fashion imagery so I made animated
fashion Holograms which I perceived the
N use being magazines and things like
that and then got involved in pulse
holography and got into portraiture and
then started doing fashion imagery on
that as well and uh did a shop window
display for Zant roads and
yeah and things like that so large scale
F fashion
images and um and then when I lived in
New York which was 1990 or
8990 I uh changed Direction totally and
went back into photographic imagery and
started making stereograms I 3D
Holograms but again still using
animation but these were more of a
documentary nature than anything M so uh
was it was this on uh Mercer Street in
New York that you did these pieces the
old Museum of holography yeah and uh so
but basically what I wanted to do was
make a a type of Imaging that was
spontaneous MH unlike you know most
holography is stuff that um you find or
whatever and then there's a lot long
deliberation process about making it to
hologram so I wanted to do something
that was totally spontaneous so I worked
out a way of making hologram from a
camera that I could carry myself all the
time so I took a photograph of 36
photographs one roll of film and then
re-registered them using an animation
technique yeah of course um nowadays uh
with video cameras and steady cams and
uh registration software this should be
a lot easier yeah you can register it on
a screen yeah yeah or maybe there's some
software that can register it for you so
I'm investigating that at the moment mhm
seems a shame though because um one of
the thing I like one of the things I
liked about
re-registering the imagery was that it
put some human contact back into the
process yes it was it was very much a
skill involved yeah which I I'm sure you
know doing it on a terminal is a skill
different different skill sets but still
skill nonetheless but it's not as much I
don't know if that's true I was going to
say it's not as much a Hands-On skill
but I guess it would be it's a tough
thing thing you know thing yes but um I
did feel that um a lot of these
processes if you take human intervention
out of them so much then they kind of
become slightly sterile MH and it was
always nice to have a bit of craft in it
so anyway maybe the craft will come
somewhere else from cuz when I was you
know re-registering these images it was
a a constant you know I didn't know how
they would turn out till actually
started re-registering them
um cuz when I looked through the images
I'd decide what was going to be the
focal
plane and uh you could con so you could
look at the image and say right that
part there is going to be on the image
plane yeah everything else is going to
be for front or behind and you could
choose that right at the end really I
mean when I shot it I obviously had a
slight idea but it often quite often
changed yeah and actually started
re-registering IM the the registration
of the images actually determines what's
in the focal plane yeah abolutely that
is very much a craft yeah absolutely and
it was uh how you shot it was a craft
you know and re-registering I have a
part of the website for little handmade
portraits where we use a small amount of
images maybe about 8 to 10 just to give
a static three-dimensional uh hologram
and uh I I went through the same thing
as far as trying to think of what am I
sacrificing if I want to go digital with
this rather than just traditional
photography yes yes it is a is a qu you
know a big uh issue really and
um yeah one that's got to be bro there
mhm but uh anyway we will see we will
see I can always go back to the old
hands- on method but the last one I did
which was some time ago um I seem to
remember it took me about a couple of
months to do because I there were 72
images which I well two lots of 36 I
montaged a foreground and a background
and both the foreground and the
background had to have corresponding Ms
so I I kind of montaged the image face
and so that was a a bit too much work I
got too involved in the process so this
this will give me a chance to step back
a bit and maybe start fresh yeah yeah
now I know I've been on a website of
yours it's personal website that
contains your photography do you also
have a website for the Hologram so
someone could see these I do it's rather
out of date it's in uh it's in Japan
well it's one I did in Japan and it's
actually on uh the oh okay yeah I
remember actually on the the guy called
Earth free rescued it from Japan and
this is now on the um consal for median
website the
khm
dode and uh I'll have to look up the
website L yeah I can do a search and uh
find the url cuz I want to include you
know a link to you know some of your
work to go along with the show as well
yes oh that would be good I've got to
update it it's rather old but um yeah no
have to thank us for rescuing it
otherwise it would have been lost
forever yeah they've been doing this
they've got quite a few holography sites
up there nothing's lost forever on the
web I there's actually a few websites
that go around and they spider all the
websites that are in existence and they
store it on their computers and you can
go there and do a search and find
websites that have been off the web for
years yeah so everything's still there
if you can so you got to find it you got
to find it do you ever think about
coming to the states to do any of your
Workshop programs um well we're got to
get this one off the ground sure sure I
understand people um have mentioned it
and uh yes of course I would be
interested in doing I mean obviously
there's a thing where you know
holography is kind of equipment
dependent and so you couldn't offer the
whole thing and you could only offer
what equip you know within the equipment
available mhm but uh the idea is to try
and get some teaching elsewhere and
hopefully encourage some people to come
to Richmond as well yeah that might want
to you know do the stereogram work or
the pulse
work did you ever hear anything from bis
I haven't heard from bis for years yeah
last I heard he was living in Oklahoma
City or something oh really huh getting
into shiatsu but I haven't heard from
for years it would be good to get in
contact with him yeah I have a videotape
of you that he recorded of you working
at the Museum of holography down in the
lab oh wow you know that' be good to see
that yeah I may I may take a few
Snippets of that at some point and uh
show people oh no that would be great
would you like that yeah yeah absolutely
that's might look a little young there
so it be
hor yeah how how the years go huh yeah
they fly past if you don't mind me
asking how old are you now oh 28
I I'm 45 now oh okay which is uh I find
quite scary yeah yeah I'm going to hit
50 in January right that's really scary
got the Big 5 that's it you know it's
almost like you know this is the last
part of my life now oh that's it that to
go it's true though it's true yeah we
still got lots of years in here 20 30
yeah I don't know it's all it's all an
attitude I imagine I'm still going to be
working away when I'm 75 I'll never
finish work I'll be I'll be working when
I pass pass away you know so I mean
things go a little you know progress
takes a little longer you know but uh
we're still working away mhm let me ask
you this do you find more excitement in
holography now or or back when you were
say younger at in New
York I think I still find it just as
exciting MH and um what about the
response of people to holography there's
seems to be almost a drought of exhibits
and yeah well I mean the the response of
people to holography seems to be equally
as amazing you know and there's a whole
load of people that come in and say wow
I've never seen anything like it yeah to
this day huh yeah yeah well and they
haven't seen them you see cuz they've
you know they're coming up you know 20y
old maybe haven't seen Holograms like
that mhm cuz I haven't been around and
uh it's it's kind of different working
in it now because um before it was
definitely on The Cutting Edge of
Technology well now it it it's just
different yeah yeah it doesn't and a lot
of competing Technologies yeah yeah well
it doesn't seem high tech anymore it
just seems different which is probably a
good thing for holography because you
know holography suffered from anything
it was being kind of
over I don't know uh what's the word I'm
looking for like people expected too
much from it they expected Star Trek and
things like that yeah project projected
entertainment within their living rooms
and things of that nature yes yes and
now that's you know not it doesn't have
such a reputation to live up to
unfortunately you still get the odd
thing in the papers where someone says
oh and they're going to be holographic
projections and you have to explain to
people that no they're not holographic
projections you know there're something
else you know so it still has that
problem
but I mean
people a lot of people had a very
negative conceptual idea of holography
you know because of all these promises
that it failed to keep up to but now
I've now got a new generation of people
coming up and they all seem very excited
about it and uh we'll see and also hphy
doing very well in the art world at the
moment you know we got um James
Terrell showing his Holograms as major
art pieces where are those shows at uh
where he recently showed some at the
Royal Academy in London okay summer show
but I think he's showing all over the
world now most of these folks are
artists in the traditional sense that
they've worked with uh other media and
holography just peaked an interest and
they decided to do a few pieces with
holography yeah yeah that's been case
for so many years I have mixed feelings
about that but I guess you know yeah I I
think uh most holograph probably do but
it's not only holography I mean most
bigname
artists will commission Studios to make
their work you know I had an art studio
an artist studio not long ago my
neighbor all he did was make work for a
famous artist you know yeah and he was a
sculptor so it's it's not just an
holography it's it's a bit annoying that
holography
per se have been able to get large shows
for themselves on the back of their own
work yeah but I think it it goes across
the board I mean art is a business and
uh uh For Better or For Worse or
whatever and it's um a lot of the people
that make you know the money are people
getting other people to make their work
for them you know yeah yeah so it's not
always like that yeah anyway so what are
your future plans I mean 10 years from
now where do you see Patrick Boyd well
um well hopefully uh running a very
successful holography school okay with
um courses more than once a
month now will you instruct do you plan
on instructing these courses yourself or
do you see the day come when I'm
instructing you'll be more in
administrative position well I'm
organizing it and instructing it and
also uh getting guest teachers in in
Yaki bergstein is the one so far but
hopefully that will increase the other
specialisms mhm so someone coming in
downstairs very
nice that's okay and it's good it's good
to hear people yes yes there's people
here yeah there's um there's quite a lot
going on here and uh yeah also you know
I'm still interested in
shooting um photographic footage for
Holograms and making Holograms again do
you see the day when you will have no
choice but to move on to digital
holography um no I think there's a
there's a there's a future for
traditional holography I mean you can
tell the difference when you look at a
digital hologram and uh
also yeah no no no I can't I can't see I
can just see traditional holography at
the moment yeah at the moment I mean
even when you make a digital
hologram you still have to um well
unless you get someone else to make it
for you you know
um there's still a lot of Technology
involved yeah all swings and roundabouts
really I imagine the printer would be
the most expensive part of the U of that
process yeah I mean basically um when
you make a digital hologram you have
a there's a setup involved and uh yeah I
mean well they are they're extremely
these digital holographic printers or
whatever are extremely expensive yeah
who's manufacturing those well we do
here oh you're manufacturing yeah that
that's the main core of our business is
the
technology making these machines now and
the folks that are purchasing them the
companies what are the applications that
they're using them for security I'm
entering security okay tickets and
things like that well I want to wish you
a lot of luck continued success it's
been a long time since we've had a
chance to talk to one another it's been
great to catch up how's Allentown
allentown's doing well good still have
the same house yes excellent you know my
wife and I put a lot of years into uh
refurbishing the house the the girls
like we had like I spoke to you on
Saturday they're they're grown yeah and
uh out of the house and uh you you got
it back to yourself now how many
children do you have two two two what
are their ages HH is 12 and Tabitha's 10
wow HH was famously featured in a
hologram okay baby mhm and uh but it
doesn't seem to have affected him too
much much yeah he's still doing well and
uh yeah no if you ever hear of bis let
us know what he's up to yeah I've looked
them up a couple times on the web and I
found a few things but uh nothing that
was current yeah I try to find everybody
yeah oh got Hill
surface at some point all right well
just to let the Hol talk listeners know
we have uh links on the website to uh
Patrick's Workshop programs and they're
running now in London and uh you can
become a part of those because they're
running around the calendar year the
last week of each month
AB excellent excellent all right I'll
send you the the address for the my
personal holography website all right
Patrick thank you pleasure I'm sure the
listeners are very happy to hear your
voice and that's what holot Talk's all
about you know we read about all these
people on the web but we don't really
get a chance to hear them or hear them
speak and this gives them everyone an
opportunity to actually put a you an
element to uh these holograph that
everyone reads about okay all right
brilliant brilliant now I'm going to
have to gem up on my technology and work
at how to download this to my iPod as
well oh yeah that's just an automatic
process I mean there's there's a thing
now where you can hook your iPod up and
it'll just download the show overnight
and it'll be waiting for you in the
morning isn't that amazing I'm I'm
getting emails from people that listen
to them uh going to work in the morning
on the buses and stuff and it's a whole
new ball game now doing well doing well
site still looks good yeah excellent all
right okay listen speak to you soon okay
take care Patrick thanks bye
bye